[music]
>> Welcome to the 2026 release wave one
launch edition of Business Central.
In this session, we're talking about
what's new in server and database. My
name is Kenny Pontopidan and with me I
have Jens Miller Peterson.
And we take care of the AL runtime.
The main investments in this release
wave are three things. Make it faster,
more effective document layouts, and
hardening or security.
And this distributes over highlights
such as enhanced MCP server,
better memory protection in the AL
runtime, index management, analysis mode
support in AL, document reporting, and
and security. And whenever you see these
small icons with a little teacher,
that's actually because we have breakout
sessions where you can learn more. So in
this sessions, it's more like an
overview session at least for these
topics.
Yes, so the first topic here is the
enhancements that we have built to the
MCP server.
In autumn, we presented the MCP server
for Business Central. And since then,
we've been working on making it even
better, more accurate, etc. I want to
highlight the MCP protocol compliance,
which means you can use other MCP
clients, and also the one hitting there
as number five, the file support using
resources, allows you to now take out
data from Business Central and do for
instance statistical analysis on it.
But I recommend that you go watch the
session on MCP server where all of these
topics will be covered in detail.
Now, another thing we have spent quite a
bit of time on in this release is to
improve how the server uses memory. We
have lowered the memory footprint per
tenant, and more importantly actually,
we have optimized the base 64 handling.
We realized that one of the common
causes of varying performance was
basically memory pressure, and a lot of
the memory pressure comes actually from
AL code doing things requiring a lot of
memory. So what we have introduced in
this release, and the work is ongoing,
is we've created a new platform code
unit for
dealing with base 64 conversion. Because
for OData returns,
they are converted into strings using
base 64 convert. So there is a new
platform code unit, and then we have
modified the existing code units to make
use of this new platform code unit, and
also introduced a method which allows
you to put the result of this into a
stream, also reducing the memory
pressure from this operation.
The new platform code unit has a
significantly lower memory footprint
than the older implementation.
What this means to you
is
actually very simple. You don't need to
change any code. What you'll see is
fewer out of memory exceptions, but also
AL errors where we have caught the
excessive memory usage.
So you basically need to react to those
and put limits in.
We cannot generate arbitrarily large
base 64 strings. If you try to do
something on a 15 GB document, you will
now see these new errors. So overall,
you see
an improved performance,
and particularly if you make use of the
new stream overloads.
And I probably also, if your friends are
using this, the performance of the your
environments will go up Yes.
>> because memory pressure hurts everyone,
not only your
sessions.
>> It's not only your session. This is
putting pressure on the whole system.
Now, we're not done with the memory
work. You should expect us to do more on
this. We will add telemetry
also for partners on large JSON
documents, large XML documents, etc. And
at some point, we are also going to put
in limits on the sizes of objects. In
addition to that, we keep working on
optimizing our memory usage
to give you a more responsive system.
Now, another new thing we've added is
the ability to get more insights into
your index usage. Now we're talking more
over to the database size, not not the
memory usage, but how much space and you
use for indexes in the database, and
also whether these indices are used.
This is also covered in a special
session, but I want to highlight that
with this new capability, we also add
the ability for you to remove indices
that is not needed for this particular
environment. You can turn
a metadata defined index off. You can
also turn it back on. And we also have
these auto-tune indexes, we call them
when we have detected an index would
help. You can also remove those if you
want to reclaim the size that these are
using. Plus, having a lot of indexes can
make write operations smaller, not
smaller, but slower. Yeah.
Again,
watch the specific session on this
topic.
And another feature that resides in the
database is
analysis mode or analysis mode views.
Analysis mode is a hugely popular
feature with with Business Central
users. And in this release wave, we
allow AL developers to include analysis
view definitions in their apps.
So this is covered in detail in the in a
breakout session, so check that
in the description.
But basically, it's the the flow is that
as as a developer, you use the client to
define your analysis view. You export it
to JSON. You put that into your app with
some extra metadata, and now this is
available
whenever users open this particular
page.
Okay, let's shift gears towards
reporting, more like document reporting.
Um
in this release wave, we are starting to
modernize document reporting more than
we have done in the previous releases,
or we're continuing that investment, may
maybe I should say that. Um a couple of
things. First of all, we are updating
the Word add-in for document reports
with better UI, with search in the data
picker, and with an an easy way to
define tables. So there's a breakout
session for that. Go check out that
after this session if you're interested
in in document reporting.
In this space, we also made it possible
or introduced a way to control life
cycle of layout, not only document
layout, any layout in the system.
Over the last probably three years, we
have added abilities for Excel layouts
and investing in Word layouts. Both of
these features are meant for end users
to create their own layouts, upload them
to Business Central. So for that
process, we realized that some
organizations would like to have a
little bit control over when this is one
of these layouts ready to use and when
it is still in draft. So you can see
this new status on report layouts that
goes from a draft into pending approval
to approved and even retired. So go
check the document reporting breakout
session to learn more. So no more just
changing the layout and see the havoc it
causes when you send that to customers.
Yeah, that's kind of the general idea of
it, yes.
Yes, and now to everybody's favorite
topic,
security.
So there's been we have hardened the URI
validation in the HTTP client, so that
we now limit more [clears throat]
outgoing calls from your AL code.
This is not something you can opt out of
in hosted environments, but for
on-premises, you can, because you might
be calling specific services that you
are hosting on your own network. Because
in general, what this will do is it'll
stop you from calling internal
port numbers, etc. But in on-premises,
we have created two server settings.
One for enabling disabling this
functionality, and then a more
fine-grained control where you can
actually specify the allowed addresses
that you would still want to call.
So if you're running on-premises, you
might want to check this out. This has
been backported to 26, version 26 and
27, which is wave 1 2025 and wave 2
2025, and it is in effect in the
service.
Now, another security improvement we
have made is that we have made it
possible to use intra security groups
for for auth in an on-premise scenario
as well.
By enabling the service setting enable
intra groups on prem.
It will now fetch enter ID security
groups
on login for this user and that means
you can now
give the users permission based on
security groups.
And speaking of permissions, then we
have also added
um more ability to analyze permissions.
There is a new page for analyzing it
which gives you a permission overview.
Again, we have a breakout session going
into more details on this topic.
Now, we've also updated our security
guide in the documentation where we have
gathered the learnings from our internal
secure future initiative. We have
gathered the feedback that we've gotten
at conferences and generally just
updated it with how we have made the
system more secure.
I want to highlight the security
scenarios guide that has been added
where you can look at how it affects you
and your environment. So, go check out
the BC
the security section in the
documentation.
And you thought we were done, but
there's just sneaked in one little bonus
which is new telemetry.
We have um added telemetry for B MCP
configuration changes, for MCP usage,
but also in the client telemetry you can
now see the users hardware and network
speed in the page view telemetry as well
as uh we we have financial reporting
usage and life cycle that was added in
the last release wave. So, if you use
telemetry to monitor environments,
there's some new things that you can use
there. And who doesn't use telemetry?
Exactly, everyone does. Um
and of course everything with telemetry
is uh documented under
aka.ms/bctelemetry.
So, go check out the new signals if you
want to uh monitor those.
We're almost at an end. Uh
for learning more, uh these are the
these are the the main uh parts of of uh
the Microsoft learn. BC developer is
taking you to the developer things like
index management and analysis mode.
Security as as Jens mentioned was uh
is the security guide and telemetry is
the telemetry documentation.
If you like this kind of content, these
sessions, there are related sessions
both the breakouts we have been talking
about in this
um and others,
they are available down here in um
in the the description for the for the
video. Uh some of them are also
highlighted in the end of this video to
to learn more, just click directly on
them.
And that's all that Jens and I had for
you in this session. Yeah, it's easy to
make it short when we just put
everything else in breakout sessions.
Well, that's what managers do, we
delegate. So, um
thanks a lot for watching.
Uh in the end of this video we are with
introducing general resources. If you
don't know don't know know those, stay
tuned, but Jens and I are done for now,
so. Thank you. Thank you.
We have compiled a number of general
resources that we believe are key both
for partners, but also Business Central
customers. Most Some of these are
partner, some of them are also for
customers. So, the first one is
called aka.ms/bcall.
This is a partner resource for that
contains lists of every other aka link
that is needed for you to understand
anything about both the Business Central
product, but also processes around it.
We call these aka links because they're
called aka.ms and then for for
something. And with Business Central
links we all always prefix with BC and
then something.
The next one is our partner network
social media for for Business Central
partners, Viva Viva Engage. So,
aka.ms/bcvivaengage
is where you go and interact with other
partners. It's not open for customers,
so this is where you can ask uh
questions, interact with the product
group, interact with with with each
other
um in a in a closed network.
Secondly, the third link is for both
partners and customers we call office
hours. So, office hours is something we
do once or twice a month from the
product group engaging with the
community about new features or things
we want to discuss. aka.ms/bcofficehours
is the is the the place where you go to
find out about upcoming events.
These are recorded. I believe the
recordings are available only to
partners, but the live events are
available to customers as well.
Fourth link is YouTube, our YouTube
channel. I'll talk about that
in the next slide and LinkedIn in the
next slide.
And then finally for for Microsoft
partners, the BC's
aka.ms/bcpartnerportal
is where you get
a lot of the resources as a partner such
as compete decks,
pitch decks and a lot of other
resources.
For LinkedIn, this is our product
group's LinkedIn profile. We have 30K or
more followers, so both partners and
customers. This is the place where we
from the product group put in news and
small bits of information outside the
official channel. So, follow us
on LinkedIn to learn what's happening
right now
in in this in the around the product.
Um and then
uh also on our YouTube channel where
this is where you're probably watching
this, aka.ms/bcyoutube.
We put in not only these launch editions
twice a year, but also
copilot and AI video shorts, tips and
tricks, technical deep dives, under the
hood.
Uh we even have this what's cooking
where we put little nuggets of of videos
out for new features that are even
coming in on the YouTube channel before
uh they're coming in the release notes.
So, watch
and maybe uh bookmark us on YouTube and
also notice all the playlists. So, that
all the content is also organized in
areas, not only all the videos. So, if
you have an area that has special
interest such as analytics,
um you can find an
a playlist and kind of see all the
content related to that.
And that's it. That is truly it. We
won't
there will be no more, so thank you for
watching all the way to the end and
again have a great day. Thank you.